<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3.xsd" version="0.3" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>sbgn.org</sitename>
    <base>http://www.sbgn.org/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.12.0</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
      <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" />
      <namespace key="1">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4">sbgn.org</namespace>
      <namespace key="5">sbgn.org talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6">Image</namespace>
      <namespace key="7">Image talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="274">Widget</namespace>
      <namespace key="275">Widget talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Documents/Specifications</title>
    <id>96</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4106</id>
      <timestamp>2016-03-18T17:45:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rodrigue</username>
        <id>66</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Activity Flow language */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__TOC__
This page provides a summary of the state of the '''public specifications'''. You can also access [[Documents/All specifications | all specifications]]. More details are available elsewhere about the [[Nomenclature | nomenclature of SBGN]]. 
All documents and source files are available in the [http://sourceforge.net/projects/sbgn Subversion repository for SBGN on Sourceforge.net].

== Process Description language (formerly Process Diagram language) ==

The SBGN ''Process Description'' (PD) language shows the temporal courses of biochemical interactions in a network.  It can be used to show all the molecular interactions taking place in a network of biochemical entities, with the same entity appearing multiple times in the same diagram.

The public specification for SBGN Process Description language Level 1 Version 1.3 can be accessed through Nature Precedings: [http://precedings.nature.com/documents/3721/version/4 doi:10.1038/npre.2011.3721.4].

For end-users more than software developers a [[media:Sbgn_PD-level1-user-public.pdf| user manual]] is also available.

To report an error or to comment on the SBGN Process Description specification, please use the [https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=178553&amp;atid=1082245 dedicated PD L1 tracker]

== Entity Relationship language ==

The SBGN ''Entity Relationship'' (ER) language allows you to see all the relationships in which a given entity participates, regardless of the temporal aspects.  Relationships can be seen as rules describing the influences of entities nodes on other relationships. 

The public specification for SBGN Entity Relationship language Level 1 Version 2.0 can be accessed through Journal of Integrative Bioinformatics: [https://sourceforge.net/p/sbgn/code/HEAD/tree/EntityRelationship/tags/Level1-Version2/sbgn_ER-level1.pdf?format=raw doi:10.2390/biecoll-jib-2015-264].


To report an error or to comment on the SBGN Entity Relationship specification, please use the [https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=178553&amp;atid=1170625 dedicated ER L1 tracker]

== Activity Flow language ==

The SBGN ''Activity Flow'' (AF) language depicts the flow of information between biochemical entities in a network.  It omits information about the state transitions of entities and is particularly convenient for representing the effects of perturbations, whether genetic or environmental in nature.

The public specification for SBGN Activity Flow language Level 1 Version 1.2 can be accessed through Journal of Integrative Bioinformatics: [{{activity-flow-current}} doi:10.2390/biecoll-jib-2015-265]

To report an error or to comment on the SBGN Activity specification, please use the [http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?func=add&amp;group_id=178553&amp;atid=1175366 dedicated AF L1 tracker].</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
