<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3.xsd" version="0.3" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>sbgn.org</sitename>
    <base>http://www.sbgn.org/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.12.0</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
      <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" />
      <namespace key="1">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4">sbgn.org</namespace>
      <namespace key="5">sbgn.org talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6">Image</namespace>
      <namespace key="7">Image talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="274">Widget</namespace>
      <namespace key="275">Widget talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Events/SBGN-1/SGBN-1 Discussion Notes: Resolutions</title>
    <id>241</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1163</id>
      <timestamp>2008-10-08T00:22:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ltaddeo</username>
        <id>6</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;div class=&quot;superhead2&quot;&gt;Feb. 12, 2006 discussions about unanswered questions&lt;/div&gt;

''(Discussions moderated and notes taken by M. Hucka.)''

'''M. Hucka:''' One of the questions that we were left with from earlier today is whether PPI implies the need for a 3rd type of view. What was the result of discussions?

'''H. Kitano:''' The conclusion seems to be that there's a different model in PPI, and PPI needs a view of this model. It's not the same model that underlies entity-relationship and state-transition diagrams. He proposes the following levels of definition:

[[image: Sbgn1-discussion.jpg | right]]

* model: something in CellML or SBML, a machine-readable form
* view: this is “how to graphically represent a model”, like an entity-relationship (MIM-style) or state-transition (PDN-style) diagram

* layer
* abstraction
* levels
* versions

'''P. Ghazal:''' The conclusion seems to be that if you're talking about protein-protein interaction, it falls under category of an ER type of view. If you're talking about a process, it falls under the Kitano type of state-transition view. If you're talking about a hierarchy, it falls under the Edinburgh type of view. Now here's a different question: does SBGN support data without an underlying model?

'''U. Dogrusoz:''' There seem to be 2 model-layer-view constructions going on. The ER and ST are 2 views of an underlying conceptual model of something, but they also act as 2 models themselves. Your diagrams are 2 views of those two models.

''(There was additional undirected discussion. Unfortunately, I was trying to think through the issues and failed to take adequate notes during the rest of this session. — M. Hucka.)''</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
