<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3.xsd" version="0.3" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>sbgn.org</sitename>
    <base>http://www.sbgn.org/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.12.0</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
      <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" />
      <namespace key="1">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4">sbgn.org</namespace>
      <namespace key="5">sbgn.org talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6">Image</namespace>
      <namespace key="7">Image talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="274">Widget</namespace>
      <namespace key="275">Widget talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>LibSBGN/ValidationEntryPage</title>
    <id>763</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2990</id>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T15:45:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tczauderna</username>
        <id>67</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Validation Topics */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Validation Topics==

* List of current rules: [[LibSBGN/ValidationRules|ValidationRules]] 
* Currently, libSBGN rules are written in Schematron. See [[LibSBGN/SchematronHowto|SchematronHowto]]

==Syntax for @see Entries==

Validation rules in libSBGN should be tagged with a &quot;see&quot; attribute that refers to an SBGN specification that points to a validation rule. 

&lt;code&gt;sbgn-(SBGN_LANG_ABBREV)-L(LEVEL_NUM)V(VERSION_NUM)-(SPEC_ENTRY)#(BULLET_NUM)&lt;/code&gt;

* SBGN_LANG_ABBREV - pd, er, af
* LEVEL_NUM - Digit
* VERSION_NUM - Digit or number with decimal
* SPEC_ENTRY - Digits separated by periods indicating the section where the rule is described. 
* BULLET_NUM - Digit indicating the bulleted item describing a rule.

Example: sbgn-pd-L1V1.3-3.5.2.2#1

==Rule Categories (Roles)==

Rules are tagged using the following categories to denote severity and status. 

* error - Failure to pass this rule type results in invalidation
* warning - Point to recommendations; failure to meet these recommendations does not result in invalidation.
* unimplemented - Represent &quot;stubs&quot; for rules that remain to be implemented.
* untestable - Rules that are that are untestable. Such rules may result from the need to have expert knowledge of a biological system to carry out the validation.
** Example: If more than one set of stoichiometries can be applied to the flux arcs of the process then the stoichiometry of the flux arcs must be displayed. (sbgn-pd-L1V1.3-3.5.2.1#8)

==Error Test Files==

'''Creators of error test files should create both the correct and incorrect cases.'''

===Naming Convention===

Test files containing errors are named using the following components: 

ruleId-assertionId_pass/fail-errorCount_testCount (

* Error code for rule 
* If multiple assertions are made then which one is being tested (in the order they appear in the ruleset).
* pass/fail, whether the file passes or fail the rule followed by an error count of any existing errors. 
* Use testCount if multiple files test the same rule. 
* If multiple rules are broken, the name should take the ruleId of the first rule broken. 

Example: pd10102-3_fail-1_1.sbgn

The file failed rule pd10102 assertion 3 with 1 error. If more than one file tested this rule, then the final 1 would uniquely identify this file.</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
