<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3.xsd" version="0.3" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>sbgn.org</sitename>
    <base>http://www.sbgn.org/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.12.0</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
      <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" />
      <namespace key="1">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4">sbgn.org</namespace>
      <namespace key="5">sbgn.org talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6">Image</namespace>
      <namespace key="7">Image talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="274">Widget</namespace>
      <namespace key="275">Widget talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nomenclature</title>
    <id>428</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1995</id>
      <timestamp>2010-02-10T22:26:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SBGNWikiSysop</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Language versus notation */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">In order to decrease confusion when talking about SBGN, it is important to use a consistent nomenclature. The following describes what should currently be used.

== Language versus notation ==

SBGN specifications propose symbols, ways to organise them, but also 
semantic rules to analyse the resulting representations. SBGN &quot;drawings&quot; 
can be translated into English, but also into computer readable formats. 
Those specifications really propose true languages. SBGN is therefore made 
up of three &lt;b&gt;languages&lt;/b&gt;.

== What are the languages? ==

PD is a language that permits the description of all the processes taking 
place in a biological system. The ensemble of all these processes 
constitute a Description.

ER is a language that permits the description of all the relations 
involving the entities of a biological system. The ensemble of all these 
relations constitute a Relationship.

AF is a language that permits the description of the flow of activity in a 
biological system.

== Nomenclature ==

The three languages of SBGN should be referred to as:

* the Process Description language
* the Entity Relationship language
* the Activity Flow language

abbreviated as:

* the PD language
* the ER language
* the AF language

----

A specific representation of a biological system in one of the SBGN 
languages should be referred to as:

* a Process Description map
* an Entity Relationship map
* an Activity Flow map

abbreviated as

* a PD map
* an ER map
* an AF map

----

The corpus of all SBGN representations should be referred to as:

* Process Descriptions
* Entity Relationships
* Activity Flows

The capitalization is important. PD, ER and AF are names of languages. As 
such they must be capitalized in English. This is not the case of the 
accompanying noun (language or map).

== Graph, diagram or map? ==

A graph is a very technical term that belongs to mathematics and is 
uncommon in biology. Diagram is a concept that encompasses more than just 
graph. Examples are Venn diagrams for instance. Therefore, we recommend 
using the term map for SBGN representations. Those representations 
effectively permit users to travel and orient themselves in a biological 
system. Map is also the term most frequently used by the different 
communities, whether in metabolism, signaling or genomics.</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
