<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.3.xsd" version="0.3" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>sbgn.org</sitename>
    <base>http://www.sbgn.org/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.12.0</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
      <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" />
      <namespace key="1">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4">sbgn.org</namespace>
      <namespace key="5">sbgn.org talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6">Image</namespace>
      <namespace key="7">Image talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="274">Widget</namespace>
      <namespace key="275">Widget talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Symbols/unit of information for BA</title>
    <id>1091</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4151</id>
      <timestamp>2016-04-11T07:32:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lenov</username>
        <id>11</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">''by Vasundra Touré''

An unit of information for a biological activity in AF illustrates the nature of the entity from which the activity comes from. It is always represented with a biological activity glyph. The unit of information can provide two types of information: the nature of the entity represented by the shape of the unit of information and the name of the entity represented by a label in the unit of information.

&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-BA.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;



There are six types of unit of information that can characterize a biological activity, as described below:

{|
|1) Macromolecule - represents a very large biochemical substance, usually a protein, a nucleic acid or a complex sugar. It’s unit of information is represented by a rectangle with rounded corners.

|&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-macro.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;

|-
|2) Simple chemical - represents a small biochemical substance, usually an atom, a mono-atomic ion, a salt, a solid metal, etc. It’s unit of information is represented by a circular container.

|&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-simplechem.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;

|-
|3) Nucleic acid feature - in SBGN represents a fragment of a macromolecule carrying genetic information. It’s unit of information is represented by a rectangle whose bottom half has rounded corners.

|&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-nucleicaf.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;

|-
|4) Unspecified entity - represents the entity type that is unknown or simply not relevant for the purposes of the maps. It’s unit of information is represented by an elliptic container.

|&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-unspec.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;

|-
|5) Complex - represents a biochemical entity composed of other biochemical entities, whether macromolecules, simple chemicals or other complexes. It’s unit of information is represented by an octagon container.

|&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-complex.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;

|-
|6) Perturbation - represents a physical phenomena that influence a biochemical network, such as a light pulse or a change in the temperature. It can also be more complex and not well defined, for instance, glucose deprivation or stress. It’s unit of information is represented by a modified hexagon container having two opposite concave faces.

|&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-perturb.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;
|}


The following example shows the transcription regulation of the gene GAS by STAT1. We can see that the protein STAT1 (a macromolecule) and the gene GAS (a nucleic acid feature) needs to form a complex in order to activate the transcription of GAS mRNA.

&lt;center&gt;
{{#icon:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-transcription.png |||| corner iradius11}}
&lt;/center&gt;



Download the unit of information for a biological activity image as (from the more semantic to the more generic): [...]

[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo_BA.sbgn|SBGN-ML]] ]
[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo_BA.gml|GML]] ]
[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo_BA.graphml|GraphML]] ]
[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-BA.svg|SVG]] ]
[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo_BA.odp|Open Document Format]] ]
[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo_BA.ppt|PowerPoint]] ]
[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-BA.pdf|PDF]] ]
[ [[media:Symbol-UnitOfInfo-BA.png|PNG]] ]</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
